Register of the World War II subject collection
Hoover Institution Archives
- Subject File, 1936-1994 (Boxes 1-57)
  - United States (Boxes 54-56)
    - Miscellany, 1941-1946, 1965 (Boxes 38, 44)
      Relates to U.S. military activities and civil defense during World War II, including manuals, servicemen's newspaper issues, bulletins, newsletters, leaflets, letters to and from American soldiers, and a mimeographed transcript of an NBC television program, The Decision to Drop the Bomb.
  - Yugoslavia, 1945 (Box 42)
    Mimeographed typescript of the agreement between the Yugoslav government and the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration relating to the provision of civilian relief in Yugoslavia at the end of World War II.
- Oversize File, circa 1939-1945 (Map case)
  Charts, maps, and photocopies of instruments of surrender.
  - Hitler Youth hierarchy diagram (originally housed in box 22)
  - 62 colored charts and maps
    Issued by the Comite d'Histoire de la 2eme Guerre Mondiale, concerning occupied France and illustrating the suffering of people and the actions of the resistance groups in France.
  - Photocopies of the instrument of surrender of Japan to the Allied Powers, 1945 September 2
  - 18 maps outlining Allied and Axis positions in various parts of the world, mainly in Western Europe, 1944
    Includes a few post-war maps.
- Memorabilia, circa 1939-1945 (Memorabilia cabinet)
  Military insignia, pair of horse's spectacles, pin, and office stamp.
  - Japanese military insignia for the ranks of major general, colonel, lieutenant colonel, and major in the Japanese Army
  - Pair of horse's spectacles
    Made in Luettringhausen concentration camp near Remscheid, Germany, by inmates in solitary confinement, during World War II. These spectacles were evidently used by General Rommel's horses in his North Africa offensive.
  - 1 pin and 1 office stamp from the Nazi occupation government of Norway
- Sound Recordings, 1941, 1944 (Record cabinet)
  Sound discs relating to the Burma Road and to the attack on Pearl Harbor.
  - Burma Road radio news broadcast relating to the re-opening of the Burma Road, 1944
  - Sound recording of interviews with Americans in various parts of the U.S. on the evening war with Japan was declared, relating to the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor, 1941 December 8
    Access note
    Use copy reference number: xx740_a_0002800
    Includes transcript.
- Incremental Materials (Boxes 58-101)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described. Contact us at hooverarchivesinfo@stanford.edu
- Armband embroidered with “F.F.I.,” Forces Francais de l’Interieur (Box 102)